Next up we have Richard Carter
from the University of York
with from AI to towards
an environmental Intelligence.
Hello. Right.
So once again,
I hope you can see my slides.
That's all good.
Yeah. Brilliant.
Okay I'm going to start my timer now.
So hello.
Yeah I'm Richard Carter
from the University of York,
the Old York from the United Kingdom.
And this presentation
is about a very new project
in mind, partly artistic,
but also partly engineering and focus.
And essentially it's called kite drone.
As the name suggests,
it's a very deliberate fusion of old
and new technologies to consider along
the kind of themes I've done in the past
about how we sense, how we make sense
of a changing world
through technology, and in particular,
if we change those those infrastructures
and contexts, what would we see?
What would we learn?
What other stories would be
told through these systems?
This project is somewhat adjacent
to electronic literature.
It's doing a bit
more than perhaps what you might think of
as a typical elite project,
but it has got elements that resonate,
and it certainly comes from a place
of making digital art
where the digital is not really the point.
The point is the richness and wonder
of the world beyond its borders.
I come from the Nam
June Paik school of using technology
to despise it properly, and we have enough
celebrations of technology.
It is a very new project as well.
It's essentially didn't exist
until about March this year,
so it's evolved in a breakneck pace.
The heart of this project
is a consideration of environmental
sensing in the guise of the much heralded
new AI technology.
So language, vision, models, etc.
and thinking about
what are their implications
for seeing and thinking going forward?
The digital world,
no question, has an extremely difficult
relationship with the environment
in terms of the energy that's used,
the waste that's generated at every stage
of the lifecycle of digital technologies.
And that bothers me as an artist who uses
digital technologies as their medium.
That's something
I am not particularly happy about.
But that said, I think it's worth
noting that although contemporary
AI technologies have been critiqued
for their environmental impact,
things were bad before.
It wasn't as if things were great
even before these technologies kind of
came onto the scene,
and it was certainly not looking good.
We've got these systems now,
and certainly in the very sort of
generalized, mythologized sense
in which they're pitched towards us.
And earlier iterations of technology
marketed as AI,
a common refrain is that they will
somehow save the planet.
They're advanced analytical techniques.
That number crunching capability
was somehow going to sort everything out,
and we don't have to worry
too much about their impacts as a result.
And that has been fairly robustly
critiqued as a load of greenwashing.
Then that's before
we even get into thinking
quite cogently about the technology,
what it can actually measure,
map and model about the world
realistically.
Nevertheless,
we are here, and it is very likely,
I think, that this technology
in its current form, will persist
in some form of future and will be
part of the public political tool set
through which environmental issues
are seen and understood by many people.
People are going to query ChatGPT.
They are not going to read
the scientific paper.
So if we take that premise, then
what other possibilities do exist
for these technologies?
Can we use them fruitfully?
Can we use them thoughtfully?
Can we use them with respect to what
they actually are, rather than what
then sort of typically sold to us?
As Sabina Linnell in this vein has called
for the development
of environmental intelligence
AI that is not oriented towards
emulating human modes of thought,
human imperatives, human agency,
but actually drawing our attention to the
more than human world or non-human world.
As she frames it,
it scales its durations, its imperatives,
and how the impact our daily lives.
And it's here, then,
that my project appears in, very much
inspired by this call.
But coming out of prior work
that I've done, thinking about how we can
use drones and machine vision
as environmental platforms, I'm
doing something similar here,
but instead I'm trying to create
an AI driven sensor platform.
Very, very small compact package
that is small enough, light enough,
and low power enough.
You can carry it aboard a kite
rather than a drone, as we might
typically expect.
And I think this image actually is one
I really like taking AI outside
of its sprawling,
all consuming data center,
ripping it out there, shrinking it down,
making it small, making it vulnerable,
putting it back in its box.
Frankly, a box
you can hold and throwing it up there.
Let's see. No,
enough of these cloud computing metaphors.
Let's make that happen.
Let's make AI small again.
Let's make it vulnerable again.
Let's make it something that respects
its footprint in the world.
There is
a awful lot that I could say
about the technology of this program,
what I'm doing with it, and
I just don't have the time to go into it.
So I'm going to give a very rapid sketch.
Now, essentially,
it consists of a large lifting kite.
In this case
it was a big eight foot Delta Conine.
And below it is a sense of boom that's got
aerodynamic plates on either end
that sort of stabilized,
that boom in the winds aloft.
Attached to that is a small computing
package, typically a Raspberry Pi.
And then attached to that package
is all manner of different sensors.
I've primarily been working with images
because that's what I understand best.
But there will be more sense
as they are attached to it.
Hopefully very, very soon.
But in essence, once we've got all that,
what the Raspberry Pi is doing
is it's taking in that data,
feeding it into a small, large vision
model
and setting various tasks
and analysis on it.
The models I've been using are Alibaba,
clouds, Quinn and Google's Gemma.
2 to 4 billion parameters.
So these are really quite small models,
very much edge case instances.
And frankly pulling them to work,
seeing what they can do.
The whole lot is controlled
in a manner typical of a drone actually.
So there's a
there's a kite net, you log into the kite,
it has its own Wi-Fi address,
and that allows for commands to be down,
commands to be up
linked video, imagery and data to be down,
linked in real time as well.
So again very much like a typical drone.
So okay,
we've got this very elaborate system.
Then we've gone to all the trouble
of hauling it up.
What does it actually do.
What am I trying to get it to do?
So in terms of visual data,
I'm simply trying to get the thing
to classify the scene sensibly, to
go, okay, I have this scene before me
at an altitude of 200ft.
What am I looking at?
What are the natural features
in that scene?
And particularly
using a land class sort of
star filters, which are kind of typically
for what we use for satellites.
I'm bringing it down here and saying,
okay, classify
this terrain according
to these different land class types.
It turns out that's incredibly hard.
Language vision
models are trained on people and things,
and it only gets worse
the smaller they get.
And so essentially, it's
very difficult to get it to pay attention
to the natural world.
The natural world is an interesting
backdrop.
Surely you're interested in cars.
Surely you're interested in people.
Surely you are interested in buildings.
Well, the answer is no.
No I'm not.
But it's very hard
to get it to steer away from that.
And even when it does point out a natural
scene, it's like there was a bush.
There's a tree over there somewhere.
Well that's fantastic.
What do we learn from that? Very little.
So I'm trying to wrestle
with this technology
and ultimately its failings
and its paucity
are so different from the rich works
of environmentally literature
that we are used to think of J.R.
Carpenter's works, for instance.
And that work was mentioned yesterday.
And of course, we had
we had the kind of documenting
the imperceptible yesterday
that was a lovely presentation
and really got this idea
of more than human
sensing in all its richness
and all its alien.
These language
vision models are wholly incapable
of doing anything remotely as clever
as that without a lot of work.
But that's part of the point.
You know, so many of us,
so many researchers,
rush to get these exhausting technologies
into their work to see what they can do,
and that's absolutely fine.
But it's also good to have projects
which point out, you know what?
They're rubbish.
There are so many things they don't do,
they don't do well.
They're not very effective
at to highlight their failures,
to highlight their failings.
And ultimately, by way of that,
getting us to remind ourselves of a world
that is so much richer
than these technologies,
so much more alien
in it's becoming more than human voices
that are not reducible to straightforward
modalities of data that cannot be put
inside the neat black boxes we otherwise
wish the world could be put into.
That's part of the idea.
But nevertheless, you might think, okay,
where's the angle going on in all of this?
So ultimately, what I hope to do
and what I have been doing,
I should say, is once the system
classifies the landscape,
those classes and those short descriptions
associated with each class in terms of
what it's seeing are then used as lookups
and a vector database to extract material
of kind of various kind of books
and articles like put inside the system.
And they are all works by different
writers such as Jennifer Gabriel.
You'll see Mia Bennett,
who are all thinking about the nature
of environmental sensing and sense
making, what it can do, what it can't do,
what its limitations are.
So the idea is that
the system is actually using what it sees
as a framing query,
and is overlaying the visual landscape
with some of these extracts from these,
from these different books
and the eventual output,
not that you can really see it
here, is effectively a hypertext window.
You have the visual scene and you can see
the different machine vision boxes.
You can click on them and you can follow
through some of the materials
that the system thinks is most appropriate
for sort of characterizing that scene.
So it sees a distant hill,
it sees a river, it sees a farmland.
Well,
what are these authors written about?
The intersection of farmland
and digital sensing.
What is the relationship
between digital sensing and rivers?
It's never quite a one on one
correspondence, but I rather like that.
Actually.
I like the strangeness of
some of the outputs that come out of that.
Reading the landscape
as a prompt for reflection,
rather than some immediate insights
and the kind of narrow sense of the word.
So again, part of the idea is
the system is generating
a meditation on the nature of digital
sensing and sense making what it does
not see, what it does
not know, the things that it cannot do
when it comes to characterizing human
and more than human relationships.
So coming up to near the end, very good.
So I'm going to be the first to admit
this is an incredibly brief presentation
on a very, very complex project.
I've had to be very schematic.
I hope that was enough to at least
give you a guide and some interest.
One long term goal of this project
actually is not artistic at all.
I would like to develop this technology
so that it's robust enough
and capable enough
that you could actually imagine
using it instead of a drone
to gather environmental data.
Indeed, it may even be desirable.
It's unlikely to achieve that aim, but
that's part of the esthetic aspirations,
this idea of imagining another world
and imagining another world.
Seriously.
All right then, let's make it happen.
Let's actually see what it would do,
what it would look like,
what are the challenges
involved in doing so?
And that's something that's actually
quite important to me in terms of modeling
what another world would look like,
what another sort of speculative sensory
landscape may ultimately resemble as well.
And eventually what I hope to do
is because the thing
has kind of Wi-Fi downlink,
you can access it on your phone.
It's kind of accessible to anyone.
As a broadcast stream.
I'd love to be able to do performances
with this apparatus.
Once it's up in the air,
there's a gathering of us.
We can annotate the data
that it's generating in real time,
have our own different perspectives,
and have a sort of a collaborative process
for mapping the landscape with the
AI is just a tiny part of that.
It's really us working
with more than human elements all around
us, seeing what we learn,
seeing where they may ultimately take us.
And on that note, I think I'm out of time.
Thank you very much for listening.